<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sesame Open Science</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/</link><description>Recent content on Sesame Open Science</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Prework</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/collection/prework/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/collection/prework/</guid><description>&lt;p>Welcome to the 
&lt;a href="https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/">Introducing Yourself Online&lt;/a> workshop! We look forward to meeting you. Before attending the workshop, please complete the following prework.&lt;/p>




&lt;h2 id="set-up-rstudio-cloud">Set up RStudio Cloud
 &lt;a href="#set-up-rstudio-cloud">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Sign up for a free RStudio Cloud account at 
&lt;a href="https://rstudio.cloud/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rstudio.cloud/&lt;/a> before the workshop. I recommend logging in with an existing Google or GitHub account, if you have one (rather than creating a new account with another password you have to remember). I want you to be able to work from your own laptop in this workshop, but Cloud is an important back-up plan should you run into troubles.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>More open abstracts?</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/thought/202411_open_abstracts/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/thought/202411_open_abstracts/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstracts are increasingly important given the rise of large language models (LLM) and generative AI. While OpenAlex provides a source of open abstracts in addition to Crossref, the takedown of abstracts from OpenAlex by two major publishers points to an increased commodification of abstracts.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>




&lt;h3 id="the-case-for-open-abstracts">The case for open abstracts
 &lt;a href="#the-case-for-open-abstracts">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Launched in 2020, the 
&lt;a href="https://i4oa.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Initiative for Open Abstracts (I4OA)&lt;/a> advocates and promotes the unrestricted availability of abstracts of scholarly output, particularly journal articles and book chapters, in trusted repositories where they are open and machine-accessible. This has gained increased relevance with the rise of large language models (LLM) and generative AI. Access to high-quality textual content for training purposes is highly sought after, with the risk of further commodification by publishers and by developers of generative AI models and tools.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Comments on EC Council Conclusions on scholarly publishing</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/thought/202306_ec/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/thought/202306_ec/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="featured_202306_ec.png" alt="featured image">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>On May 23, 2023, the Council of the European Union approved a set of conclusions on&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>&amp;lsquo;High-quality, transparent, open, trustworthy and equitable scholarly publishing&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> &lt;em>(see 
&lt;a href="https://data.consilium.europa.eu/doc/document/ST-9616-2023-INIT/en/pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pdf&lt;/a>).&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>Below are some of my thoughts on these conclusions.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I think these Council Conclusions are very welcome and important, as they align with, and in turn can support, a number of important current developments in how open access is perceived and implemented. One of these is the growing awareness, also among research institutions and funders, of the inequality and unsustainability of APC-driven open access publishing, especially by commercial or otherwise revenue-driven publishers. Another is a growing emphasis on important qualitative aspects of open access, in particular immediacy and open licensing.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Developments in peer review</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202304_oscd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202304_oscd/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Research infrastructure as a social norm</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202301_ape/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202301_ape/</guid><description/></item><item><title>DIAMAS</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/diamas/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/diamas/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="in-the-transition-towards-open-access-institutional-publishing-is-challenged-by-fragmentation-and-varying-service-quality-visibilityand-sustainability">&amp;ldquo;In the transition towards Open Access, institutional publishing is challenged by fragmentation and varying service quality, visibility,and sustainability.&amp;rdquo;
 &lt;a href="#in-the-transition-towards-open-access-institutional-publishing-is-challenged-by-fragmentation-and-varying-service-quality-visibilityand-sustainability">&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>To address this issue, the Horizon Europe project DIAMAS will:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Map the current landscape of Institutional Publishing Service Providers (IPSPs)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Coordinate and improve the efficiency and quality of IPSPs by developing an Extensible Quality Standard for Institutional Publishing (EQSIP)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Formulate community-led, actionable recommendations and strategies for institutional leaders, funders/sponsors/donors, and policymakers.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>— 
&lt;a href="https://diamasproject.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DIAMAS website - Welcome to the DIAMAS project&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Crossref metadata for preprints: Discussions and recommendations</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_metaarxiv_crossref/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_metaarxiv_crossref/</guid><description>&lt;p>In 2016, Crossref launched a metadata schema for ‘posted content’ with the aim of better accommodating the metadata needs for preprints, working papers, theses, reports, and related outputs, which are not typically peer-reviewed. In 2021, Crossref formed an Advisory Group (AG) to discuss how the quality of metadata for preprints using this schema could be improved. The group focused on four topics: 1) preprints as an article type (rather than subtype of posted-content); 2) relationships to/from preprints; 3) versioning; and 4) withdrawal/removal of preprints. The recommendations that resulted from the group’s deliberations have been published previously. Here we provide further background to the recommendations and report more details of the discussions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The availability and completeness of open funder metadata</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_qss/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_qss/</guid><description>&lt;p>Research funders spend considerable efforts collecting information on the outcomes of the research they fund. To help funders track publication output associated with their funding, Crossref initiated FundRef in 2013, enabling publishers to register funding information using persistent identifiers. However, it is hard to assess the coverage of funder metadata because it is unknown how many articles are the result of funded research and should therefore include funder metadata. In this paper we looked at 5,004 publications reported by researchers to be the result of funding by a specific funding agency: the Dutch Research Council NWO. Only 67% of these articles contain funding information in Crossref, with a subset acknowledging NWO as funder name and/or Funder IDs linked to NWO (53% and 45%, respectively). Web of Science (WoS), Scopus, and Dimensions are all able to infer additional funding information from funding statements in the full text of the articles. Funding information in Lens largely corresponds to that in Crossref, with some additional funding information likely taken from PubMed. We observe interesting differences between publishers in the coverage and completeness of funding metadata in Crossref compared to proprietary databases, highlighting the potential to increase the quality of open metadata on funding.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Preprints and open preprint review: a workshop on innovations in scholarly publishing</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_upstream/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_upstream/</guid><description>&lt;p>Researchers, librarians, policy makers, and practitioners often complain about the scholarly publishing system, but the system also offers exciting opportunities to contribute to innovations in the way academic findings are disseminated and evaluated.
At the Dutch Open Science Festival, which took place at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam on September 1st 2022, we organized one of the ‘community-led’ workshops to discuss some of these developments, focusing on preprints and open preprint review. Participants discussed the opportunities offered by these innovations, and reflected on ways in which these innovations may complement, or perhaps even replace, traditional journal publishing practices.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Q&amp;A about Wiley's decision to open its abstracts</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_leidenmadtrics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_leidenmadtrics/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post Ludo Waltman and Bianca Kramer reflect on today’s announcement that Wiley is joining the Initiative for Open Abstracts (I4OA) and is going to make abstracts openly available through Crossref.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>SCOSS</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/scoss/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/scoss/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="scoss-supported-open-science-infrastructure-provides-the-scientific-and-scholarly-community-with-resources-and-services-to-access-share-and-assess-research-scoss-is-a-pragmatic-approach-to-investing-in-open-infrastructure-one-that-allows-stakeholder-institutions-to-participate-in-the-direct-and-immediate-funding-of-essential-infrastructure-it-is-not-the-only-pathway-or-means-to-invest-in-open-infrastructure">“SCOSS-supported open science infrastructure provides the scientific and scholarly community with resources and services to access, share, and assess research. SCOSS is a pragmatic approach to investing in open infrastructure; one that allows stakeholder institutions to participate in the direct and immediate funding of essential infrastructure. It is not the only pathway or means to invest in open infrastructure.”
 &lt;a href="#scoss-supported-open-science-infrastructure-provides-the-scientific-and-scholarly-community-with-resources-and-services-to-access-share-and-assess-research-scoss-is-a-pragmatic-approach-to-investing-in-open-infrastructure-one-that-allows-stakeholder-institutions-to-participate-in-the-direct-and-immediate-funding-of-essential-infrastructure-it-is-not-the-only-pathway-or-means-to-invest-in-open-infrastructure">&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>— 
&lt;a href="https://scoss.org/what-is-scoss/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SCOSS website - What is SCOSS&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>For SCOSS, I am working together with participating infrastructures to develop strategies for achieving their funding goals, as well as to contribute to the general strategy of SCOSS.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Measuring what matters - open to interpretation ?</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202210_lis/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202210_lis/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Talking Points: Bianca Kramer on publishing</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_elife/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_elife/</guid><description>&lt;p>After spending 15 years as a librarian for the life sciences and medicine at Utrecht University, Bianca Kramer recently started her own consulting firm, Sesame Open Science, to provide advice and support for projects related to open science. Throughout her career Kramer has been a strong advocate for open science and innovations in scholarly communication. Here she discusses how academic publishing and the role of libraries and librarians have changed over recent decades, and what she hopes the publishing landscape will look like in ten years.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Open abstracts in SSH – current state and challenges</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202209_triple/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202209_triple/</guid><description/></item><item><title>New developments in preprinting and preprint review</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202209_npos/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202209_npos/</guid><description>&lt;p>The workshop introduced participants to preprinting and preprint peer review. Participants were invited to discuss the opportunities offered by these new approaches to scholarly publishing and peer review, and to reflect on different ways in which these new approaches may complement the traditional journal publishing system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Workshop together with Jeroen Bosman (Utrecht University), Jeroen Sondervan (Utrecht University) and Ludo Waltman (CWTS)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Preprint discoverability</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202208_asapbio/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202208_asapbio/</guid><description>&lt;p>With thanks to Jeroen Bosman for analysis of newspaper coverage of COVID19 preprints!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bianca Kramer is Keeping Tabs on Open Research</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202207_upstream/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202207_upstream/</guid><description>&lt;p>Being encouraged to keep “open tabs”, has been an interesting experience - turning something that’s usually guilt-inducing (“I really should be reading this…!”) into something that at least feels productive (“Oh, I could use this for the Upstream blog!”).
In the end, did I actually read more because I kept conscious track of all those open tabs? Or less, because I bookmarked the links for this blog and then neglected to read the actual content? I’ll leave that an open question&amp;hellip; Either way, this post lists some of the things that caught my eye over the last month or two.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>UKRI / Research Consulting</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/rc-ukri/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/rc-ukri/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="a-new-study-commissioned-by-uk-research-and-innovation-ukri-to-develop-a-monitoring-and-evaluation-me-framework-for-their-open-access-policy-this-framework-will-seek-to-enable-ukri-and-the-broader-sector-to-assess-progress-towards-open-access-levels-of-compliance-with-the-ukri-policy-and-its-overall-effectiveness-the-me-framework-will-also-aim-to-establish-how-open-access-publication-trends-affect-academic-practices-and-society-where-possible">&amp;ldquo;A new study commissioned by UK Research and Innovation (UKRI) to develop a monitoring and evaluation (M&amp;amp;E) framework for their Open Access policy. This framework will seek to enable UKRI and the broader sector to assess progress towards Open Access, levels of compliance with the UKRI policy and its overall effectiveness. The M&amp;amp;E framework will also aim to establish how Open Access publication trends affect academic practices and society, where possible.&amp;rdquo;
 &lt;a href="#a-new-study-commissioned-by-uk-research-and-innovation-ukri-to-develop-a-monitoring-and-evaluation-me-framework-for-their-open-access-policy-this-framework-will-seek-to-enable-ukri-and-the-broader-sector-to-assess-progress-towards-open-access-levels-of-compliance-with-the-ukri-policy-and-its-overall-effectiveness-the-me-framework-will-also-aim-to-establish-how-open-access-publication-trends-affect-academic-practices-and-society-where-possible">&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>— 
&lt;a href="https://www.research-consulting.com/developing-a-monitoring-and-evaluation-framework-for-the-ukri-open-access-policy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Research Consulting website - Developing a monitoring and evaluation framework for the UKRI Open Access policy &lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Open science - where from? where to?</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202206_uu/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/talk/202206_uu/</guid><description>&lt;p>Workshop together with Jeroen Bosman (Utrecht University Library)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Language Diversity in Scholarly Publishing</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202206_coki/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202206_coki/</guid><description>&lt;p>There is a lot of lip service paid to the idea of diversity in scholarly publishing and often diversity of language is used as an example. But while the groups that work actively in languages other than English have been making this point consistently and forcefully, it has had limited traction in the scholarly anglophone literature, some nice counterexamples notwithstanding.
To address this gap, we have mapped the 122 million objects in Crossref up to the end of May 2022 to languages (based on titles and abstracts, where available) and done an initial analysis. The results are a mix of the expected and surprising.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>COKI Open metadata report</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/coki_open_metadata_report/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/coki_open_metadata_report/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="open-automated-workflow-to-compare-coverage-and-quality-of-open-metadata-sources">Open, automated workflow to compare coverage and quality of (open) metadata sources.
 &lt;a href="#open-automated-workflow-to-compare-coverage-and-quality-of-open-metadata-sources">&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>In this project, we assess and compare the value added by OpenAlex to Crossref metadata, both in coverage of publications and other research output (with and without DOIs) as well as in coverage of metadata (including identifiers) for authors, institutions, publication venues and disciplines.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We are working to extend the project to provide an automated workflow to compare any two (open) metadata sources.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Advancing open access in the Netherlands after 2020: from quantity to quality</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_insights/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_insights/</guid><description>&lt;p>The purpose of this article is to explore options to further open access in the Netherlands from 2021. Its premise is that there is a need to look at the qualitative aspects of open access, alongside quantitative ones. The article first takes stock of progress that has been made. Next, we suggest broadening the agenda by involving more types of actors and other scholarly formats (like books, chapters, proceedings, preprints and textbooks). At the same time we suggest deepening the open access agenda by including several open access dimensions: immediacy, diamond open access, open metadata, open peer review and open licences. To facilitate discussion, a framework is proposed that allows specifying these actions by the a) aspects of open access they address (what is made open access, how, when and where it is made open access, and copyright and rights retention), b) the actors that play a role (government, research institutions, funders) and c) the various levels at which these actions can be taken: state as goal, set as policy, legalize and promote, recognize and reward, finance, support with infrastructure. A template is provided to ease the use of the framework.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>An Open Knowledge Base for the Netherlands: Report of a Community Workshop</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_zenodo_okb/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_zenodo_okb/</guid><description>&lt;p>The concept of developing a national Open Knowledge Base for the Netherlands (NL-OKB) has been proposed in response to the strategic needs of the research community in the Netherlands. In parallel with the work of the 
&lt;a href="https://www.vsnu.nl/files/documenten/Domeinen/Onderzoek/Open%20access/Engelstalige%20samenvatting%20opdracht%20werkgroep.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dutch Taskforce on Responsible Management of Research Information and Data&lt;/a> addressing these opportunities and the preparation of a 
&lt;a href="https://www.dialogic.nl/en/projects/haalbaarheidsstudie-open-knowledge-base/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">feasibility study by Dialogic&lt;/a>, interested stakeholders were convened with the goal of identifying expert and user-community interests in and need for an NL-OKB.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>OA Diamond Journals Study</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202103_zenodo_oadjs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202103_zenodo_oadjs/</guid><description>&lt;p>From June 2020 to February 2021, a consortium of 10 organisations undertook a large-scale study on open access journals across the world that are free for readers and authors, usually referred to as “OA diamond journals”. This study was commissioned by cOAlition S in order to gain a better understanding of the OA diamond landscape.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The study undertook a statistical analysis of several bibliographic databases, surveyed 1,619 journals, collected 7,019 free text submissions and other data from 94 questions, and organised three focus groups with 11 journals and 10 interviews with hosting platforms. It collected 163 references in the academic literature, and inventoried 1048 journals not listed in DOAJ.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Style your site colors</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/color-themes/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/color-themes/</guid><description>&lt;p>You can totally customize your site&amp;rsquo;s theme colors within minutes of
creating a new site. Read on to find out how, and decide which of the
three options meets your needs.&lt;/p>




&lt;h2 id="use-a-color-theme">Use a color theme
 &lt;a href="#use-a-color-theme">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Hugo Apéro includes 8 built-in color themes that work &amp;ldquo;out of the box.&amp;rdquo;
This means you can use a color theme to quickly customize the look of your site
without needing to write any CSS. You can select the color theme in your &lt;code>config.toml&lt;/code> file. Scroll down to find:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Style your site typography</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/fonts/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/fonts/</guid><description>&lt;p>As with 
&lt;a href="../color-themes">color themes&lt;/a>, you can completely customize your site&amp;rsquo;s fonts within minutes of creating a new site. How you do it depends on how much control and customization you need.&lt;/p>




&lt;h2 id="embedded-fonts">Embedded fonts
 &lt;a href="#embedded-fonts">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Hugo Apéro includes 6 embedded fonts that work &amp;ldquo;out of the box.&amp;rdquo; We selected 3 serif and 3 sans-serif options that we thought looked good with this theme, in our humble opinions. All embedded fonts include 
&lt;a href="https://www.marksimonson.com/notebook/view/FakevsTrueItalics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">real italics&lt;/a> so you may &lt;em>emphasize&lt;/em> to your &lt;em>heart&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em> content &amp;#x2764;&amp;#xfe0f;! How to choose?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>An evergreen post</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/evergreen/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/evergreen/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="rendering-mathematical-equations">Rendering mathematical equations
 &lt;a href="#rendering-mathematical-equations">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Examples from the 
&lt;a href="https://www.mathjax.org/#demo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mathjax demo&lt;/a>.
But they work with &lt;code>katex&lt;/code> as well.&lt;/p>




&lt;h3 id="rmarkdown">Rmarkdown
 &lt;a href="#rmarkdown">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In &lt;code>.Rmarkdown&lt;/code> documents, you can use either&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>I4OA</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/i4oa/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/i4oa/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="i4oa-calls-on-all-scholarly-publishers-to-open-the-abstracts-of-their-published-works-and-where-possible-to-submit-them-to-crossref">I4OA calls on all scholarly publishers to open the abstracts of their published works, and where possible to submit them to Crossref.
 &lt;a href="#i4oa-calls-on-all-scholarly-publishers-to-open-the-abstracts-of-their-published-works-and-where-possible-to-submit-them-to-crossref">&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>— 
&lt;a href="https://i4oa.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">I4OA website&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>The Initiative for Open Abstracts (I4OA) is a collaboration between scholarly publishers, infrastructure organizations, librarians, researchers and other interested parties to advocate and promote the unrestricted availability of the abstracts of the world&amp;rsquo;s scholarly publications, particularly journal articles and book chapters, in trusted repositories where they are open and machine-accessible.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>COVID preprints</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/covid_preprints/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/covid_preprints/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="two-repositories-containing-code-and-data-on-covid-19-related-preprints-and-links-from-preprints-to-published-journal-articles-derived-from-open-metadata-and-visualization-of--their-distribution-over-time">Two repositories containing code and data on COVID-19 related preprints and links from preprints to published journal articles, derived from open metadata, and visualization of their distribution over time.
 &lt;a href="#two-repositories-containing-code-and-data-on-covid-19-related-preprints-and-links-from-preprints-to-published-journal-articles-derived-from-open-metadata-and-visualization-of--their-distribution-over-time">&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Role: contributor together with Nicholas Fraser (ZBW) (COVID preprints)&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>Role: personal project (links to published journal articles)&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>Time period: May 2020 - ongoing&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CSS Grid Scaffold</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/css-grid-scaffold/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/css-grid-scaffold/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="grid-is-the-very-first-css-module-created-specifically-to-solve-the-layout-problems-weve-all-been-hacking-our-way-around-for-as-long-as-weve-been-making-websites">“Grid is the very first CSS module created specifically to solve the layout problems we&amp;rsquo;ve all been hacking our way around for as long as we&amp;rsquo;ve been making websites.”
 &lt;a href="#grid-is-the-very-first-css-module-created-specifically-to-solve-the-layout-problems-weve-all-been-hacking-our-way-around-for-as-long-as-weve-been-making-websites">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;em>— 
&lt;a href="http://chris.house/blog/a-complete-guide-css-grid-layout/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Chris House, A Complete Guide to CSS Grid Layout&lt;/a>&lt;/em> &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>




&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview
 &lt;a href="#overview">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Since I began building websites in Y2K, I&amp;rsquo;ve lost count how many times the phrase &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;there&amp;rsquo;s got to be a better way to do this&amp;rdquo; has passed my lips. Most times, while fighting with floats and widths of content and sidebars or just basically trying to get something beside something else without using a stupid &lt;code>TABLE&lt;/code>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Built-in Contact Form</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/built-in-contact-form/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/blog/built-in-contact-form/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="formspree-logo.png" alt="Formspree Logo">&lt;/p>




&lt;h2 id="formspreehttpsformspreeio-makes-it-easy-to-receive-submissions-from-html-forms-on-your-static-website">
&lt;a href="https://formspree.io" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Formspree&lt;/a> makes it easy to receive submissions from HTML forms on your static website.
 &lt;a href="#formspreehttpsformspreeio-makes-it-easy-to-receive-submissions-from-html-forms-on-your-static-website">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;hr>




&lt;h3 id="functional-form">Functional Form
 &lt;a href="#functional-form">&lt;svg class="anchor-symbol" aria-hidden="true" height="26" width="26" viewBox="0 0 22 22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
 &lt;path d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="currentColor">&lt;/path>
 &lt;path d="M3.9 12c0-1.71 1.39-3.1 3.1-3.1h4V7H7c-2.76.0-5 2.24-5 5s2.24 5 5 5h4v-1.9H7c-1.71.0-3.1-1.39-3.1-3.1zM8 13h8v-2H8v2zm9-6h-4v1.9h4c1.71.0 3.1 1.39 3.1 3.1s-1.39 3.1-3.1 3.1h-4V17h4c2.76.0 5-2.24 5-5s-2.24-5-5-5z">&lt;/path>
 &lt;/svg>&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This theme has a &lt;strong>form-to-email&lt;/strong> feature built in, thanks to the simple Formspree integration. All you need to activate the form is a valid recipient email address saved in the front matter of the form
(&lt;code>/content/forms/contact.md&lt;/code>). Of course, the example shown below (&lt;code>your@email.here&lt;/code>) must not be used. Please use your actual email address.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 13:38:41 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/contact/</guid><description>&lt;p>** Contact page don&amp;rsquo;t contain a body, just the front matter above.
See form.html in the layouts folder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Formspree requires a (free) account and new form to be set up. The link is made on the final published url in the field: Restrict to Domain. It is possible to register up to 2 emails free and you can select which one you want the forms to go to within Formspree in the Settings tab.
**&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Typography Styles &amp; Element Examples</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/elements/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 12:27:33 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/elements/</guid><description>&lt;div class="flex-l">
 &lt;div class="w-50-l pr4-l">
 &lt;h6 class="ttu tracked black-30 pv3 mt5 bt b--black-10">Font Sizes&lt;/h6>
 &lt;div class="w-100 overflow-x-auto">
 &lt;table class="w-100 mb2">
 &lt;tbody>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td class="tc f-headline b b--black-10 bg-white-60 v-base">A&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc f-subheadline b b--black-10 bg-white-60 v-base">A&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc f1 b b--black-10 bg-white-60 v-base">A&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc f2 b b--black-10 bg-white-60 v-base">A&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc f3 b b--black-10 bg-white-60 v-base">A&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc f4 b b--black-10 bg-white-60 v-base">A&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc f5 b b--black-10 bg-white-60 v-base">A&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc f6 b b--black-10 bg-white-60 v-base">A&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td class="tc black-50 f6 fw2 pa1">6rem&lt;br>(96px)&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc black-50 f6 fw2 pa1">5rem&lt;br>(80px)&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc black-50 f6 fw2 pa1">3rem&lt;br>(48px)&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc black-50 f6 fw2 pa1">2.25rem&lt;br>(36px)&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc black-50 f6 fw2 pa1">1.5rem&lt;br>(24px)&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc black-50 f6 fw2 pa1">1.25rem&lt;br>(20px)&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc black-50 f6 fw2 pa1">1rem&lt;br>(16px)&lt;/td>
 &lt;td class="tc black-50 f6 fw2 pa1">.875rem&lt;br>(14px)&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/tbody>
 &lt;/table>
 &lt;/div>
 &lt;h6 class="ttu tracked black-30 pv3 mt5 bt b--black-10">Type Samples&lt;/h6>
 &lt;h1 class="f-headline measure-narrow lh-solid">Head&amp;shy;line&lt;/h1>
 &lt;h1 class="f-subheadline measure-narrow lh-solid">Sub&amp;shy;head&amp;shy;line&lt;/h1>
 &lt;h1 class="f2 f1-ns measure-narrow lh-title">Level 1 Heading&lt;/h1>
 &lt;p class="f4-ns measure lh-copy">One page to rule them all...well, not really. This page displays sample typography and page elements to illustrate their style. Things like headings and paragraphs showing the beautiful type scale, form elements, tabular data, and image layouts just to name a few.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>101 Innovations in Scholarly Communication</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/101_innovations/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/101_innovations/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="we-are-interested-in-the-way-information-is-created-shared-and-processed-in-academia-this-is-reflected-in-a-number-of-related-activities-aimed-at-charting-the-changing-scholarly-communication-landscape">We are interested in the way information is created, shared, and processed in academia. This is reflected in a number of related activities aimed at charting the changing scholarly communication landscape.
 &lt;a href="#we-are-interested-in-the-way-information-is-created-shared-and-processed-in-academia-this-is-reflected-in-a-number-of-related-activities-aimed-at-charting-the-changing-scholarly-communication-landscape">&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>We created an overview of current and expected developments and models to get a grip on the abundance and variety of research tools used across the research cycle. We are charting the creation and availability (supply side) and usage (demand side) of research tools. We continue to investigate why researchers use certain tools, to find out what tool usage patterns can tell us about the changes in scholarly communication, and, finally, to uncover the driving forces behind the creation and innovation of research tools and the (lack of) interoperability of these tools.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Contributors</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/contributors/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/contributors/</guid><description>&lt;p>Thank you to the people who have contributed both technical and creative skills:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/jeroenbosman" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jeroen Bosman &amp;#x1f4a1;&lt;/a> (for developing lots of ideas and workshop formats together over the past ten years and counting)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://www.github.com/nehamoopen" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Neha Moopen &amp;#x1f9d9;&lt;/a> (for convincing me to build a website using RMarkdown and Github Pages and pointing me to the Hugo Apéro theme)&lt;br>&lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>And also: 
&lt;a href="https://www.apreshill.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alison Hill &amp;#x1f34b;&lt;/a> for developing great step-by-step 
&lt;a href="https://hugo-apero-docs.netlify.app/start/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">documentation&lt;/a> for creating a Hugo Apéro website.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>License</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/license/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/license/</guid><description>&lt;p>Unless otherwise noted, all content on this site is released under a 
&lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;center>
&lt;i class="fab fa-creative-commons fa-2x">&lt;/i>&lt;i class="fab fa-creative-commons-by fa-2x">&lt;/i>
&lt;/center></description></item></channel></rss>