<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>blogpost on Sesame Open Science</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/categories/blogpost/</link><description>Recent content in blogpost on Sesame Open Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/categories/blogpost/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Preprints and open preprint review: a workshop on innovations in scholarly publishing</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_upstream/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_upstream/</guid><description>Researchers, librarians, policy makers, and practitioners often complain about the scholarly publishing system, but the system also offers exciting opportunities to contribute to innovations in the way academic findings are disseminated and evaluated. At the Dutch Open Science Festival, which took place at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam on September 1st 2022, we organized one of the ‘community-led’ workshops to discuss some of these developments, focusing on preprints and open preprint review.</description></item><item><title>Q&amp;A about Wiley's decision to open its abstracts</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_leidenmadtrics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_leidenmadtrics/</guid><description>In this post Ludo Waltman and Bianca Kramer reflect on today’s announcement that Wiley is joining the Initiative for Open Abstracts (I4OA) and is going to make abstracts openly available through Crossref.</description></item><item><title>Bianca Kramer is Keeping Tabs on Open Research</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202207_upstream/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202207_upstream/</guid><description>Being encouraged to keep “open tabs”, has been an interesting experience - turning something that’s usually guilt-inducing (“I really should be reading this…!”) into something that at least feels productive (“Oh, I could use this for the Upstream blog!”). In the end, did I actually read more because I kept conscious track of all those open tabs? Or less, because I bookmarked the links for this blog and then neglected to read the actual content?</description></item><item><title>Language Diversity in Scholarly Publishing</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202206_coki/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202206_coki/</guid><description>There is a lot of lip service paid to the idea of diversity in scholarly publishing and often diversity of language is used as an example. But while the groups that work actively in languages other than English have been making this point consistently and forcefully, it has had limited traction in the scholarly anglophone literature, some nice counterexamples notwithstanding. To address this gap, we have mapped the 122 million objects in Crossref up to the end of May 2022 to languages (based on titles and abstracts, where available) and done an initial analysis.</description></item></channel></rss>