<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects on Open on Sesame Open Science</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/</link><description>Recent content in Projects on Open on Sesame Open Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SCOSS</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/scoss/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/scoss/</guid><description>“SCOSS-supported open science infrastructure provides the scientific and scholarly community with resources and services to access, share, and assess research. SCOSS is a pragmatic approach to investing in open infrastructure; one that allows stakeholder institutions to participate in the direct and immediate funding of essential infrastructure. It is not the only pathway or means to invest in open infrastructure.” — SCOSS website - What is SCOSS
For SCOSS, I am working together with participating infrastructures to develop strategies for achieving their funding goals, as well as to contribute to the general strategy of SCOSS.</description></item><item><title>UKRI / Research Consulting</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/rc-ukri/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/rc-ukri/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;A new study commissioned by UK Research and Innovation (UKRI) to develop a monitoring and evaluation (M&amp;amp;E) framework for their Open Access policy. This framework will seek to enable UKRI and the broader sector to assess progress towards Open Access, levels of compliance with the UKRI policy and its overall effectiveness. The M&amp;amp;E framework will also aim to establish how Open Access publication trends affect academic practices and society, where possible.</description></item><item><title>COKI Open metadata report</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/coki_open_metadata_report/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/coki_open_metadata_report/</guid><description>Open, automated workflow to compare coverage and quality of (open) metadata sources. In this project, we assess and compare the value added by OpenAlex to Crossref metadata, both in coverage of publications and other research output (with and without DOIs) as well as in coverage of metadata (including identifiers) for authors, institutions, publication venues and disciplines.
We are working to extend the project to provide an automated workflow to compare any two (open) metadata sources.</description></item><item><title>I4OA</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/i4oa/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/i4oa/</guid><description>I4OA calls on all scholarly publishers to open the abstracts of their published works, and where possible to submit them to Crossref. — I4OA website
The Initiative for Open Abstracts (I4OA) is a collaboration between scholarly publishers, infrastructure organizations, librarians, researchers and other interested parties to advocate and promote the unrestricted availability of the abstracts of the world&amp;rsquo;s scholarly publications, particularly journal articles and book chapters, in trusted repositories where they are open and machine-accessible.</description></item><item><title>COVID preprints</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/covid_preprints/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/covid_preprints/</guid><description>Two repositories containing code and data on COVID-19 related preprints and links from preprints to published journal articles, derived from open metadata, and visualization of their distribution over time. Role: contributor together with Nicholas Fraser (ZBW) (COVID preprints)
Role: personal project (links to published journal articles)
Time period: May 2020 - ongoing</description></item><item><title>101 Innovations in Scholarly Communication</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/101_innovations/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/101_innovations/</guid><description>We are interested in the way information is created, shared, and processed in academia. This is reflected in a number of related activities aimed at charting the changing scholarly communication landscape. We created an overview of current and expected developments and models to get a grip on the abundance and variety of research tools used across the research cycle. We are charting the creation and availability (supply side) and usage (demand side) of research tools.</description></item></channel></rss>