<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Report on Sesame Open Science</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/categories/report/</link><description>Recent content in Report on Sesame Open Science</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/categories/report/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>An Open Knowledge Base for the Netherlands: Report of a Community Workshop</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_zenodo_okb/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_zenodo_okb/</guid><description>&lt;p>The concept of developing a national Open Knowledge Base for the Netherlands (NL-OKB) has been proposed in response to the strategic needs of the research community in the Netherlands. In parallel with the work of the 
&lt;a href="https://www.vsnu.nl/files/documenten/Domeinen/Onderzoek/Open%20access/Engelstalige%20samenvatting%20opdracht%20werkgroep.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dutch Taskforce on Responsible Management of Research Information and Data&lt;/a> addressing these opportunities and the preparation of a 
&lt;a href="https://www.dialogic.nl/en/projects/haalbaarheidsstudie-open-knowledge-base/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">feasibility study by Dialogic&lt;/a>, interested stakeholders were convened with the goal of identifying expert and user-community interests in and need for an NL-OKB.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal in convening a workshop was:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>To gather evidence on the feasibility of an NL-OKB&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To test the community interest and appetite for developing an NL-OKB&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To identify a practical pathway forward towards startup and implementation of an NL-OKB&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Over two days, 19-20 November 2020, 35 participants representing national and international organisations met in a virtual workshop. This included representatives of VSNU, NWO, NFU, SURF, DANS, CWTS and a range of Netherlands institutions alongside international stakeholders such as Crossref, ORCID, OpenAIRE, DataCite, SPARC North America, Jisc, UKRI and others.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There was strong support for an NL-OKB amongst the assembled group. The group as a whole was strongly in favour of the development of an NL-OKB run on behalf of and controlled by the academic community. Of those present, virtually all indicated they had a direct stake and interest in supporting the development of an NL-OKB. International participants were also keen to see efforts in the Netherlands succeed as an exemplar to be drawn upon. The assembled group reached a series of consensus conclusions, that taken together provide the beginnings of a roadmap for further development.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>