<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>open science on Sesame Open Science</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/categories/open-science/</link><description>Recent content in open science on Sesame Open Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/categories/open-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>DIAMAS</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/diamas/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/diamas/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;In the transition towards Open Access, institutional publishing is challenged by fragmentation and varying service quality, visibility,and sustainability.&amp;rdquo; To address this issue, the Horizon Europe project DIAMAS will:
Map the current landscape of Institutional Publishing Service Providers (IPSPs) Coordinate and improve the efficiency and quality of IPSPs by developing an Extensible Quality Standard for Institutional Publishing (EQSIP) Formulate community-led, actionable recommendations and strategies for institutional leaders, funders/sponsors/donors, and policymakers. — DIAMAS website - Welcome to the DIAMAS project</description></item><item><title>UKRI / Research Consulting</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/rc-ukri/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/rc-ukri/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;A new study commissioned by UK Research and Innovation (UKRI) to develop a monitoring and evaluation (M&amp;amp;E) framework for their Open Access policy. This framework will seek to enable UKRI and the broader sector to assess progress towards Open Access, levels of compliance with the UKRI policy and its overall effectiveness. The M&amp;amp;E framework will also aim to establish how Open Access publication trends affect academic practices and society, where possible.</description></item><item><title>101 Innovations in Scholarly Communication</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/101_innovations/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/project/101_innovations/</guid><description>We are interested in the way information is created, shared, and processed in academia. This is reflected in a number of related activities aimed at charting the changing scholarly communication landscape. We created an overview of current and expected developments and models to get a grip on the abundance and variety of research tools used across the research cycle. We are charting the creation and availability (supply side) and usage (demand side) of research tools.</description></item></channel></rss>