<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>article on Sesame Open Science</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/categories/article/</link><description>Recent content in article on Sesame Open Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/categories/article/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The availability and completeness of open funder metadata</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_qss/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_qss/</guid><description>Research funders spend considerable efforts collecting information on the outcomes of the research they fund. To help funders track publication output associated with their funding, Crossref initiated FundRef in 2013, enabling publishers to register funding information using persistent identifiers. However, it is hard to assess the coverage of funder metadata because it is unknown how many articles are the result of funded research and should therefore include funder metadata. In this paper we looked at 5,004 publications reported by researchers to be the result of funding by a specific funding agency: the Dutch Research Council NWO.</description></item><item><title>Advancing open access in the Netherlands after 2020: from quantity to quality</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_insights/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_insights/</guid><description>The purpose of this article is to explore options to further open access in the Netherlands from 2021. Its premise is that there is a need to look at the qualitative aspects of open access, alongside quantitative ones. The article first takes stock of progress that has been made. Next, we suggest broadening the agenda by involving more types of actors and other scholarly formats (like books, chapters, proceedings, preprints and textbooks).</description></item><item><title>OA Diamond Journals Study</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202103_zenodo_oadjs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202103_zenodo_oadjs/</guid><description>From June 2020 to February 2021, a consortium of 10 organisations undertook a large-scale study on open access journals across the world that are free for readers and authors, usually referred to as “OA diamond journals”. This study was commissioned by cOAlition S in order to gain a better understanding of the OA diamond landscape.
The study undertook a statistical analysis of several bibliographic databases, surveyed 1,619 journals, collected 7,019 free text submissions and other data from 94 questions, and organised three focus groups with 11 journals and 10 interviews with hosting platforms.</description></item></channel></rss>