<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Publications on Open on Sesame Open Science</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/</link><description>Recent content in Publications on Open on Sesame Open Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Crossref metadata for preprints: Discussions and recommendations</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_metaarxiv_crossref/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_metaarxiv_crossref/</guid><description>In 2016, Crossref launched a metadata schema for ‘posted content’ with the aim of better accommodating the metadata needs for preprints, working papers, theses, reports, and related outputs, which are not typically peer-reviewed. In 2021, Crossref formed an Advisory Group (AG) to discuss how the quality of metadata for preprints using this schema could be improved. The group focused on four topics: 1) preprints as an article type (rather than subtype of posted-content); 2) relationships to/from preprints; 3) versioning; and 4) withdrawal/removal of preprints.</description></item><item><title>The availability and completeness of open funder metadata</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_qss/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202211_qss/</guid><description>Research funders spend considerable efforts collecting information on the outcomes of the research they fund. To help funders track publication output associated with their funding, Crossref initiated FundRef in 2013, enabling publishers to register funding information using persistent identifiers. However, it is hard to assess the coverage of funder metadata because it is unknown how many articles are the result of funded research and should therefore include funder metadata. In this paper we looked at 5,004 publications reported by researchers to be the result of funding by a specific funding agency: the Dutch Research Council NWO.</description></item><item><title>Preprints and open preprint review: a workshop on innovations in scholarly publishing</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_upstream/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_upstream/</guid><description>Researchers, librarians, policy makers, and practitioners often complain about the scholarly publishing system, but the system also offers exciting opportunities to contribute to innovations in the way academic findings are disseminated and evaluated. At the Dutch Open Science Festival, which took place at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam on September 1st 2022, we organized one of the ‘community-led’ workshops to discuss some of these developments, focusing on preprints and open preprint review.</description></item><item><title>Q&amp;A about Wiley's decision to open its abstracts</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_leidenmadtrics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_leidenmadtrics/</guid><description>In this post Ludo Waltman and Bianca Kramer reflect on today’s announcement that Wiley is joining the Initiative for Open Abstracts (I4OA) and is going to make abstracts openly available through Crossref.</description></item><item><title>Talking Points: Bianca Kramer on publishing</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_elife/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202210_elife/</guid><description>After spending 15 years as a librarian for the life sciences and medicine at Utrecht University, Bianca Kramer recently started her own consulting firm, Sesame Open Science, to provide advice and support for projects related to open science. Throughout her career Kramer has been a strong advocate for open science and innovations in scholarly communication. Here she discusses how academic publishing and the role of libraries and librarians have changed over recent decades, and what she hopes the publishing landscape will look like in ten years.</description></item><item><title>Bianca Kramer is Keeping Tabs on Open Research</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202207_upstream/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202207_upstream/</guid><description>Being encouraged to keep “open tabs”, has been an interesting experience - turning something that’s usually guilt-inducing (“I really should be reading this…!”) into something that at least feels productive (“Oh, I could use this for the Upstream blog!”). In the end, did I actually read more because I kept conscious track of all those open tabs? Or less, because I bookmarked the links for this blog and then neglected to read the actual content?</description></item><item><title>Language Diversity in Scholarly Publishing</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202206_coki/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202206_coki/</guid><description>There is a lot of lip service paid to the idea of diversity in scholarly publishing and often diversity of language is used as an example. But while the groups that work actively in languages other than English have been making this point consistently and forcefully, it has had limited traction in the scholarly anglophone literature, some nice counterexamples notwithstanding. To address this gap, we have mapped the 122 million objects in Crossref up to the end of May 2022 to languages (based on titles and abstracts, where available) and done an initial analysis.</description></item><item><title>Advancing open access in the Netherlands after 2020: from quantity to quality</title><link>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_insights/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bmkramer.github.io/SesameOpenScience_site/publication/202106_insights/</guid><description>The purpose of this article is to explore options to further open access in the Netherlands from 2021. Its premise is that there is a need to look at the qualitative aspects of open access, alongside quantitative ones. The article first takes stock of progress that has been made. Next, we suggest broadening the agenda by involving more types of actors and other scholarly formats (like books, chapters, proceedings, preprints and textbooks).</description></item></channel></rss>